בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ע"ג, Ayin Gimmel, 73.
We pick up on the משנה, mishna, we're a little behind on
ע"ב עמוד ב. Ayin Bet Amud Bet. We have three more days
of this פרק. perek. We will be done by שבת, Shabbos, so
it's been a fun ride. We pick up with the משנה, mishna,
and the משנה mishna here towards the end brings us back to
some of the topics from the beginning, which is the question about
buying fruits, thank you, at when the, after the price has been
set at the early part of the season when the price is
still low, in order for delivery later in the season when the
price is high. And that that's not an issue of ריבית, Ribbis,
provided that, a, the price is set and that, b, the fruit
is either owned by the person who is selling it, or is
available in the market. Because then since you could buy the fruit
right now yourself at this lower price, it's okay to accept delivery
later when the price is higher. So let's take a look at
the משנה. mishna. אין פוסקין על הפירות עד שיצא השער. Ein poskin
al hapeiros ad sheyeitzei hashaar. You cannot make this arrangement for payment
now and delivery later until the market price has been published, until
there's like a fixed market price to that.
יצא השער, Yatza hashaar, once the price has been published, פוסקין אף
על פי שאין לזה יש לזה. poskin af al pi she-ein lazeh
yeish lazeh. You can make the arrangement, and even though if the
guy you're selling it to does not have possession of the fruit,
so maybe you'll say that's more like a loan, not a sale
because he doesn't even have the product he's selling you. No, because
it's available in the marketplace, and therefore even though he doesn't have,
other people have, and he could purchase it.
Now, היה הוא תחלת הקוצרים. hayah hu techillat hakatzerim. Now let's say
the guy you're buying it from, the farmer you're buying it from,
was one of the early people to harvest his fruit. So you
want to buy it from him before the price has been fixed.
But again, you're buying it for him for later delivery. פוסק עמו
על הגדיש, posik immo al hagdish, so you can do that, and
we're going to see, the punchline is, as long as he actually
has the product. So either the price has to be fixed and
it has to be available, you know, in the marketplace, and then
he doesn't have to have the product, or if you're going to
make the deal before the price is fixed, at you know, even
before at a very early stage in the season, then the person
has to actually have the product. And then it's like since he
could give you the product he has, you can do later delivery.
So therefore, פוסק עמו על הגדיש. posik immo al hagdish. So you
can make an arrangement for the, so if you
for the bundle of wheat, the pile of wheat, because he was
an early harvester. ועל העביט של ענבים, v'al ha-avit shel anavim, or
you can make an arrangement for him on the, you know, on
the container of wine, whatever an עביט avit is, like some type
of a cistern or something of wine, not a cistern but whatever,
some type of a bowl. ועל המעטן של זיתים, v'al hamaatan shel
zeitim, and on the pressing of the olives, the also like you
can arrange for a certain amount of olives. ועל הביצים של יוצר,
v'al habeitzim shel yotzer, or the, what's called the balls of clay
that are going to be turned into pots. So apparently which is
interesting, who would've thought those had a season? But maybe there's a
season when the earth was ready to be done, so now those
balls of clay are being made, even though it's, you know, one
person is
an early seller. ועל הסיד מששקעו בכבשנו, v'al hasid mishekia' b'kivshano, and
plaster once the stuff has been put into the oven, so it's
turning into plaster. So all of these things once they're basically considered
like the person has possession of them and they're ready to be
sold, even if it's only that person and it's not widely done,
you can make the arrangement then for later delivery. One second. ופוסק
עמו על הזבל כל ימות השנה. u-posik immo al hazavel kol yemot
hashanah. And you can make the arrangement for delivery of dung anytime
of the year, presumably even if he doesn't have dung, dung is
always available. רבי יוסי אומר אין פוסקין על הזבל אלא אם כן
היתה לו זבל באשפה. Rabbi Yosi omer ein poskin al hazavel ela
im ken haytah lo zavel ba-ashpah. No, no, no. Even dung, he
has to actually own the dung as well.
Why it's exactly, you know, which category this falls in? Does this
fall into a category of like יצא השער yatza hashaar where you
don't have to own it because you could buy it from other
people, or is it a case of like it's not יצא השער
yatza hashaar and you have to own it yourself? Seems to be
something of the debate. וחכמים מתירין. vachachamim matirin. And the חכמים Chachamim
allow it even though you don't have it.
Okay, so I guess we'll pause there for a moment. David, you
had a question?
Yeah, in a lot of these cases is it the actual produce
that's going to be delivered at a later date, or just because
he has this produce now, he can sell different produce?
Yeah, that's a very good question.
It's a very good question. Like, does the ownership of this produce
allow the sale but nevertheless you're not really buying this stuff? I
mean at the end of the day, right, you know, yeah it's
a good point. I mean you're not really doing a קנין kinyan
because you're only giving money, you're not doing the קנין. kinyan. But
it's a good question. It's a very good question. Right, do we
just sort of essentially need something that gives it the appearances, enough
of the pieces of it that get rid of the problem of
ריבית ribbis or the appearance of ריבית, ribbis, or you really...? really
have to be this object itself? We're going to see some cases
like that that are going to come up, so let's let's hold
that question and get back to it. Not exactly remembering the answer
but there is some relevant גמרות Gemaras that come up about that.
Okay. Now, similarly, ופוסקין עמו בשער הגבוה, uposkin imo besha’ar hagavoa, you
can make an arrangement based on the, you know, now this idea
of שער הגבוה sha’ar hagavoa means it's a funny phrase because שער
הגבוה sha’ar hagavoa sounds like high prices but שער הגבוה sha’ar hagavoa
really means a lot of produce for a certain price. Okay so
שער הגבוה sha’ar hagavoa actually means low prices so it's very confusing
we do all this to confuse you, right? It means that for
my dollar I get three... I get four bushels not three. That's
שער הגבוה sha’ar hagavoa because I get four bushels. Okay, so basically
here's the story. I go ahead and I give you the
money and the prices now are low, okay, and we assume that
they're only going... that they're only going to get higher and you're
going to give me delivery later. That's why it's a ריבית ribbis
problem. But I can actually say to you, 'Here's my hundred dollars,
we're going to go at the assumption that this stuff's going to
go I don't know for a dollar for five units, okay.' If
it turns out when it comes time for delivery the prices actually
go down and it comes out to be six units or seven
units per dollar then I want you to give me that price.
I want you to give me the lower price. Okay. So not
only are you basically giving it now with delivery later when most
likely the price will be higher right so that creates the ריבית
ribbis problem but you can even exacerbate it by saying that I
want you to basically lock in for me—now it doesn't have to
be any low price between now and delivery, but that I either
get the price now or I get the price at delivery if
that's the lower price. Okay which means that I'm pretty much insulated
from loss right? The price goes down and I get the lower
price, the price goes up and I get based on the earlier
lower price. Okay so I won't necessarily make a profit because if
the price goes down then I guess it'll be just as good
as if I had the cash on me and was buying it
now. Okay but but if the—but I but I certainly am protected
against loss. All right, so that's what you're allowed to do. Why?
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer אף על פי שלא פוסקין בשער
הגבוה, af al pi shelo poskin besha’ar hagavoa, even if you didn't
explicitly make that arrangement you could still demand the lower price when
it came time for delivery or you know if at that point
it's a lower price you can demand that why? יכול לומר
לו תן לי כזה או תן לי מעותי. Yachol lomar lo ten
li kaze o ten li ma’osai. Because look I gave you a
hundred dollars three months ago okay now the price is lower so
I could say you know what forget the delivery just give me
back the hundred dollars you owe me because the sale wasn't final.
So since I could always say at the time of delivery forget
it I'm calling off the deal just give me back my money
and then I use that hundred dollars to buy at the lower
price רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you might as well just always
be entitled to get at the lower price at the time of
delivery. All right. So this really points out why this stuff even
though it is a sale you know and it
really can start feeling like a little bit of a ריבית. ribbis.
I give you money and you're going either give me we're assuming
the price will go up so we're assuming that you're going to
give me based on today's prices which means I'll make a profit
and if the prices go down and I don't make a profit
at least I'm not going to make a loss. Okay? Certainly what
the גמרא Gemara calls one place is קרוב לשכר ורחוק מהפסד. karov
liskar verachok mehefsed. All right so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rav Assi amar
Rabbi Yochanan אין
פוסקין אלא בשער שבשוק ein poskin ela besha’ar shebashuk which seems to
be a direct contradiction to the משנה. Mishnah. You do not you
cannot do it based on the price that has been established in
the marketplace. Now is he making a difference because the משנה Mishnah
says יצא השער? yatza hasha’ar? Is there a difference between the general
שער sha’ar maybe in terms of when you know the farmers have
a fixed wholesale price that they're selling to the retailers as opposed
to a שער בשוק sha’ar bashuk which is like a fixed retail
price? You know maybe that's the difference maybe there's only something for
farmers it's not something for retailers or whatever. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says.
אמר ליה רב זירא לרב אסי, Amar lei Rav Zeira leRav Assi,
Rav Zeira said to Rav Assi, 'אמר רבי יוחנן אפילו כדורמס זו?'
Amar Rabbi Yochanan afilu kidurmos zu? Would he even say it even
like this like this? כדורמס Kidurmos was a some like huge marketplace?
Like really? Like even like this maybe you know maybe he meant
only like little local marketplaces where the prices fluctuate from one little
local market to the other? But you really you can't use like
a fixed price based on like even if it was like this
major you know mall here and like you know that set the
prices for everyplace? So he says אמר ליה לא לא אמר רבי
יוחנן אלא בשוק של עיירות. amar lei lo lo amar Rabbi Yochanan
ela beshuk shel ayarot. No no no. He was only talking about
like little marketplaces in the villages דלא קביעי תרעא היא delo kvi’i
tar’ai hi that there it's not fixed. Okay it maybe varies from
one village to the other it's not even stable in a particular
village so there he was saying that the price set in those
markets... places are not really stable prices. But yeah, if it was
a major marketplace which really was a stable price, sure, but it
does sound like that's part of his חידוש chiddush contrasting שוק shuk
to the case of maybe the משנה mishnah which was talking again
maybe more about, you know, what the farmers are selling to the
wholesalers. Okay, anyway, ולמאן דסליק אדעתיה מעיקרא ul'man desalik ada'atei mei'ikara דאמר
רבי יוחנן אפילו כדורמיס הזה d'amar Rebbe Yochanan afilu k'durmis hazeh and
the הווא אמינא hava amina that the גמרא Gemara had. It's so
funny to ask me a question on the הווא אמינא, hava amina,
that it was possible that רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan said it even
in terms of like a major market that you would not, you
couldn't use those prices. אלא מתניתין דקתני אין פוסקין על הפירות עד
שיצא השער, יצא השער פוסקין, ela matnitin detani ein poskin al hapeirot
ad sheyatza hashaar, yatza hashaar poskin, but our משנה mishnah that says
that you don't do it until the amount is established, and when
the amount is established, you know, you can basically, so how does
that, how does that fix with, fit with רבי יוחנן's Rebbe Yochanan's
statement if רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan said you can never use the
price of the market? So again, I'm trying to suggest a difference
between markets and wholesalers, but the משנה mishnah assumes not that way.
So how would, so if רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan really meant you
don't go by the price of markets, what price are you going
by? says the גמרא. Gemara. If the משנה mishnah says you do
go by fixed prices. So the גמרא Gemara says היכי משכחת לה
למתניתין? heichi mashkachat lah l'matnitin? What could be the case, or how
would you find it? So the גמרא Gemara says בחיטי דאכלי וארפי.
bechitti de'achli v'arfi. No,
it would not be a marketplace price, it would be the price
of the stuff and here this is what I was trying to
get at, the price of the grain that is in the warehouses
and on the boats דמשך תרעייהו טפי. demashach tar'eihu tfei.
There that has a more stable price. Okay, so you know, what's
currently the price, I think this is in my mind something between
like the wholesale level and the retail level, okay? You know, you
know, yeah, the price is still even in large markets have greater
fluctuation than the prices of the people that have all the grain
stored in the granaries and all the grain that's being shipped on
the boats, right? You know, and there you're talking, I think the
point is there you're talking more at the wholesale level. So those
and, you know, and because there's so much of it there, you
know, the prices have on, you know, the prices have more, are
more stable, like a, you know, stay that way for a longer
period of time.
They can charge however they want at whatever price they want.
Oh, that's also a good point, you mean like the sellers have
so much that they have more, that they can also wait more
and sell, you know, based, is that what you're saying?
It's more like the retailers, people in the store, their prices probably
fluctuate based on where they're located. Right,
right. You charge whatever you want at the שוק shuk but like...
I see, I see. Oh, that's an interesting point too. You're saying
that the wholesalers is more right, it's not as, it's not as
fickle, it's more like, you know, there's a, yeah, yeah. So something,
I think it is something of a difference of wholesale and retail.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, תנו רבנן:
tanu rabbanan: אין פוסקין על פירות עד שיצא השער, יצא השער פוסקין,
אף על פי שאין לזה יש לזה. ein poskin al peirot ad
sheyatza hashaar, yatza hashaar poskin, af al pi she'ein lezeh yesh lezeh.
So that's a restatement of the משנה. mishnah. You can make it
even though you don't have, you can sell based on that price
even though you don't have because other people have. והיו חדשות מארבע
וישנות משלוש. vehayu chadashot me'arba uyeshanot mishalosh. Now
this is a little confusing, but anyway, if the new stuff is
selling at a lower price, is selling four units per dollar, and
the and the old stuff is a higher price, three units per
dollar. People prefer old dried out wheat, it's more, you know, lasts
longer, and maybe it's more fit for grinding into flour or something.
Okay, now here's the problem. I'm going to buy from you the
new stuff at the cheaper price, at the four per dollar. You're
going to deliver it to me three months from now.
Now normally you could do that. But the reason normally you could
do that is because when you deliver it to me later, you're
really delivering it to me the same product you would have delivered
to me today, except you're just delivering it at a later time.
And I could have bought that product today. So there's like a
certain logic which is you're not doing me such a favor by
giving it to giving it to me later since I could have
got it myself today, and therefore it's not really like I got
interest or like I earned money off of it even though it's
going to be worth more later, because the reason it'll be worth
more later is because the prices will go up. But here, what
you're going to deliver me later is old grain. Today what I'm
buying is new grain because three months from now it'll be old
or six months from now it'll be old. So what you're going
to deliver me later is not the stuff I would have bought
today. You're going to deliver me old grain. And if I would
be buying today old grain, I would have to pay a higher
price, right? Because the old grain costs more. So you can't say,
well, you could have just bought it yourself, you know, you could
have taken possession of it right now, so he didn't do you
anything by delivering it later and, you know, it just happens to
be the price right now. No, because if the thing he delivered
later were I to have bought today, I would have had to
pay more for it. Okay, so I wouldn't have paid the price
I was paying right now. So therefore, now you could have said
I could have bought it, taken it home and waited and it
would have got older in my own house, you know, but then
there was a risk of spoilage and other types of things, but
the point still is is that in this case it's not just
like, oh, the prices went up, but you know, you were entitled
to take it then. In a certain way there's almost like a
different product that you're going to be. Getting that, a product that
actually was more is was more expensive. Yes. No, so I understand,
okay, I
can make that.
Yeah, okay. So it says, okay, so היו חדשות מארבע וישנות משלוש.
Hayu chadashos m'arba v'yeshanos mishalosh. So the new stuff was going at
four units per dollar and the old stuff was three. אין פוסקין
עד שיצא השער Ein poskin ad sheyeitze hashar לחדש ולישן. Lachadash v'layashan.
So anyway, what I'm saying is רש"י's Rashi read it, this גמרא
Gemara is so terse it could mean something else. But anyway, the
רש"י Rashi says is you cannot agree on today's prices for the
new stuff to deliver it six months when it becomes old, unless
the prices of the new and the old are the same. Or
I guess unless you're willing to pay the prices of the old.
So if you're willing to pay today's prices of the old, you
can take delivery six months from now when it is old, okay?
Or if the prices of the old are the same as the
same, but you can't pay today's prices for the new and get
delivery six months from now when it becomes old. All right.
Okay. היו לקוטות מארבע וכל אדם משלוש. Hayu lakutos m'arba v'chol adam
mishalosh. Now
there are people that basically would go ahead and they would be,
you know what this almost reminds me of is the, I mean
you know, this idea of like לקט Leket of gathering the grain.
So there were people that would go from field to field and
gather grain, like the whole story in the Ruth, and you know,
sometimes they would have more than they maybe needed for their own
family if they were very vigorous about it. It sort of reminds
me of, you know, the people you sometimes see that are שלעפינג
Schlepping around their shopping carts filled with like disposable bottles, right? So
it's like, you know, they're really, you know, putting in the effort,
they're collecting all the stuff. They're not using it all for themselves,
they're going to make a little money off of it. Okay. So
you now can buy grain from the people that are the these
gatherers. That price is actually less than when you go to a
farmer. Okay, because as רש"י Rashi says, you know, it's like, it's
not, it's all maybe it's a little this and a little of
that and it's all mixed up and whatever. It's not as the
quality in general, you know, if they're picking stuff that's on the
ground, tends not always to be the same quality, gets stepped on
or whatever. So it's not exactly the same as if you buy
straight from the farmer or from anybody,
any normal any person who maybe just, you know, bought from a
farmer, but it's not because of this gathering up of all the
stuff. Okay. So היו לקוטות Hayu lakutos where were we?
מארבע, M'arba, that was going at the lower price at four per
dollar, וכל אדם משלוש V'chol adam mishalosh and normal and everybody else
was three per dollar. אין פוסקין עד שיצא השער Ein poskin ad
sheyeitze hashar ללקוט ולמכור. Lilkot v'limocher. You cannot make an arrangement for
the, you know, for the what do you call it? For this
guy. I'm going to go to a farmer, not a gatherer, and
I'm going to say, okay, I will buy it for you, but
let's what we'll agree to buy it at the at the rate
it's going now from the for the gatherers. At the rate of
four per dollar, not three per dollar, okay? Now, the question that
should be like obvious. You have to make the you have to
buy if you're buying it now for later delivery, it has to
be based on the fixed price. And the fixed price right now
is is three per dollar
for the normal farmer. Okay, but the point that the גמרא's Gemara
going to say is one minute, though. Once it's יצא השער, Yatza
hashar, okay, why is it that we can go by the fixed
price even if I don't have the stuff? When it's יצא השער
Yeitze hashar we can go by the price even though I'm not
a farmer. I don't even have the stuff, but I can sell
it to you now because I can turn around and buy it
from somebody else, right? So here I am, I'm a normal guy,
okay, and I'm going to sell it to you at and and
you say, I want to buy it at the cheaper price because
you can always turn around and buy it from the gatherers. You
don't have to turn around and buy it from a farmer, you
can buy it from the gatherers. Okay, so this now becomes an
interesting question, that really there's two fixed prices out there, a high
one and a low one, okay? So and it's basically saying is,
now the question is so then okay, you know, why should that
be a problem? Maybe
you'll be okay to accept the grain that I buy from the
like which grain am I prepared to get? The grain from the
farmers or the grain from the gatherers? So let's see the גמרא
Gemara will clarify this.
He said there's a difference in quality.
Well right, a difference in
the previous. Well right, I mean I sort of like gave away
that sort of what the גמרא's Gemara going to get at, but
that's sort of like the point here. You can't, you know, you
can't say to me, we're going to do it at the lower
price, okay? Because yeah, there's some people selling at the lower price,
okay? And the reason now the question is why not? I could
just turn around and buy from those people. So we'll see that
the גמרא's Gemara going to say the reason why not is either
because A, I would be reluctant to buy from those people, or
B, because when you're doing a deal with somebody who is not
of a locate somebody who's not one of those gatherers, the implicit
agreement is that I deliver you the higher quality of stuff. So
since that's the implicit agreement, the higher quality, we can't do the
price based on the lower quality stuff. But if it would be
I would be prepared to buy from the people who are selling
lower quality stuff and you would be prepared to accept it, then
obviously we could do it. But the גמרא's Gemara basically going to
say it's one or the other. In a normal case we can't
agree to the lower price because either I'm hesitant to buy from
those people or you're not prepared to accept that quality. So then
obviously we can't do that price.
Is that kind of ריבית Ribbis in a certain way? You get,
if you're not demanding of this person who has the higher quality,
and you're saying I want you to sell it to me at
the lower quality price?
Right. Yeah.
So he's getting a bit of a
Yeah, that's why you're not allowed to do it. You're not allowed,
because you're not, you're not going to get that lower quality stuff,
you'll get the better quality stuff.
Presumably also less of the לקט Leket stuff? Aha.
And so,
oh, that's an interesting point. So maybe the idea that it's readily
available is not so true here, there's a limited supply. That's a
very interesting thought. So that prices go up
since so many people are, are going for that.
That's an interesting thought. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say that, but that's
a good possibility. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רב נחמן...
Amar Rav Nachman... so עד שיצא השער ללוקט ולמוכר. ad she'yeitzei hashaar
lelokeit u'lemocher. So again, רש"י Rashi says עד שיצא השער ad she'yeitzei
hashaar means until the price is the same for those two. אמר
רב נחמן פוסקין ללקוטות כשער ללקוטות. Amar Rav Nachman: Poskin le'lakutos keshaar
le'lakutos. No, no, no. That's okay if you actually want to do
a deal with the gatherers based on the price that the, of
the gathered grain, that's okay. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei
Rava le'Rav Nachman, so now רבא Rava said to רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, מאי שנא לוקט דאי לית ליה יזיף מלוקט חבריה? mai shna
lokeit de'ei leis lei yazif milokeit chavrei? Why can you do a
deal with a gatherer? Because you can tell with that gatherer, even
if you don't have any of your available grain, he can turn
around and buy from his friends a gatherer. Okay, right? So that's
the idea. You don't, you don't have to have, you can buy
from somebody else. So if that's true and you can do the
deal with the gatherer at the lower
price, so
בעל הבית נמי יזיף מלקוטות? baal habayis nami yazif milakutos? So why...
so then if you buy from a normal homeowner, like a normal
guy, so why can't you buy at the lower price? Let him
turn around and buy from one of the gatherers. Okay, this is
getting to our question. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה בעל
הבית זילא ביה מילתא למיזף מלקוטות. amar lei baal habayis zila bei
milsa lemizaf milakutos. No,
no, no. A homeowner is going to be hesitant to buy from
one of those gatherers, right? Presumably those were, you know, the lower
social strata of the society or whatever, and therefore like, he's not
going to turn around and, he's going to be hesitant. It won't
be, it's not like that's an available market to him. I mean,
yes, it's theoretically available, but the reality is is he's going to,
you know, it won't be dignified in his eyes for him to
go do that, so he's not going to engage in that deal.
So that's seen as off limits to him, so he can't get
that grain.
Okay, איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, if you want, he could get the
grain but the guy won't accept it. You the buyer don't want
it. איבעית אימא מאן דיהיב זוזי לבעל הבית אפירי שפיר יהיב. Iba'is
eima man deyahiv zuzei lebaal habayis apiri shapir yahiv. If you're giving,
you're doing the deal with the homeowner and not with one of
these gatherers, you expect to get the good grain, right? You can't
say, well, you didn't say what type of grain, here, here's this
gathered grain. No, the implicit arrangement agreement is that you get the
grain that comes straight from the farmers. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara continues. אמר רב ששת אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Sheshet amar
Rav Huna אין לוין על השער שבשוק. ein lavin al hashaar she'bashuk.
You cannot borrow against the price in the market. Now what does
this mean? So רש"י Rashi has two very interesting explanations. One is,
it means the exact same thing that we've been talking until now
that's allowed, you cannot do it if you call it a loan
as opposed to a sale. Okay, so here I am, I'm going
to give money to Eli, a hundred dollars, and he's going to
give me delivery later when the prices will most likely be higher.
Okay, so I'm going to make a profit. He'll give me ten
units now, now it goes ten units for a hundred dollars, he'll
give me ten units and then it'll be worth a hundred and
twenty dollars. But that's okay because basically what I'm doing is I'm
buying them, I'm pre-buying them for later delivery. But let's say, what
I can't do is I can't say to Eli, I will lend
you a hundred dollars, okay, and you can pay me back later,
you know, pay me back when it's time to pay me back
in six months from now, go ahead and pay me, you know,
based on what that hundred dollars can buy right now, go ahead
and pay me back
with ten units. Since I've called it a loan as opposed to
a sale, okay, then he's really, he borrowed a hundred dollars and
he's paying you back stuff worth a hundred and twenty. Okay, so
one explanation is it's exactly what we said you're allowed to do,
except just don't call it a loan. Okay, you gotta call it
a sale. The other explanation רש"י Rashi has, which is a little
bit more relevant, is an issue that we've been referring to for
a long time but we have yet to have addressed directly, which
is called סאה בסאה. se'ah be'se'ah. Okay, which is basically, I can't
say, lend me a, you know,
lend me
a pint of milk or lend me a bushel of grain and
I'll pay you back later another bushel of grain. Now the point
is that happens every day, you go to your next door neighbor.
So one of the, how do you do that? So we'll talk
in a minute, maybe one of the answers will come up from
here. The reason you can't do that is, I borrow a bushel
of grain from you, and I pay you back a week from
now, maybe it's worth more. So I, it would, right, I borrowed
something and I gave it back to you and its value is
higher because the way you determine how much was the loan is
always in terms of its dollar value. So I borrowed a bushel,
I paid back a bushel, yes, but I borrowed something worth ten
and I paid back something worth twelve if I paid you back
a little later. Okay, so that you're not allowed to do. Okay,
so רש"י... Rashi... so one explanation here is, is that that is...
let me just double check רש"י Rashi here.
Oh yes, so here the idea is is that the point is
יצא השער בשוק yatza hasha'ar bashuk means that maybe I can say,
you know, you come to me David and you want to borrow
a cup of flour and we say, look, of course you can
borrow a cup of flour and pay me back the cup of
flour because there's a fixed price out there, that's what it means
יצא השער בשוק. yatza hasha'ar bashuk. Right, you know, if there's maybe
a fixed price out there, you just go to the supermarket, you
know, let's say it's a five pound bag of flour, everyone knows
exactly how much that costs and so on, so it would be
the same type of a logic, which is, is that since you
know, that's sort of readily available, like at that price and so
on and maybe the assumption is that it will remain like a
roughly fixed price. So then it's not a problem like you're going
to pay me back something that might be worth more or so
on because it's like readily available now to be buy, to be
sort of bought at that price and to give to me, so
when you give it to me later it's the same type of
logic. I guess logic is that even if the price did go
up, since you could have bought it at today's prices, you know,
and held onto it, of course then why would you have had
to borrow it from me? But you know, who knows? Anyway, the
way רש״י Rashi sort of explains it, here's the way רש״י Rashi
explains it, which might, which actually is very helpful because this is
always why you do borrow from your next door neighbor. Why do
you borrow from your next door neighbor? Convenience. Convenience, because the stores
are closed, you can't go to the store right now, whatever. Well,
one of the times you're allowed to do this type of a
thing of סאה בסאה se'ah b'se'ah is basically if you say that
look, we have to wait till my, I need flour, but my,
my, my, you know, my storehouse is locked, I have to wait
till I get the key, so can you lend it to me
just until the time that I can get the key and whatever
and then I'll pay you back. And that's actually allowed because that's
sort of like a case of יש לו. yesh lo. I could
just go ahead and get it myself once I get over this
little obstacle, right, and therefore, if I can just give you back
the flour right now, essentially I have access to it and give
it back to you right now or whatever, so it's not a
problem of like later payment when the prices might be higher. Okay?
Because I really like have that right now. Ownership?
Well, it's about, you don't have, right, well, yes, so because you
own it, that's the even though the access is somewhat limited, that's
okay. עד שיבוא בני, ad sheyavo beni, right? So you have to
own it. That's sort of like, it's what it sort of like
is before it's יצא השער, yatza hasha'ar, okay? Right? And we can
make this deal before it's יצא השער yatza hasha'ar if I own
the thing because since I could give you that thing right now,
even though there's not yet a fixed price, I can take the
money and pay you, give it later. That's the idea that if
I own it. So here too I could borrow, you know, a
bag of flour if it's locked up and I'm waiting to get
access to it because I could just, I could like it's right
available for me to give it back to you right now. Okay?
So it's not like that, you know, it's not like that problem.
So here too the question is, let's say I don't have, own
it, and it's not in my house and I'm not waiting for
the key, but there's a fixed, it's being sold in the stores
and there's a fixed price. Okay? So if it's being sold in
the stores, if there's a fixed price to it, alright, so, you
know, that's like a יצא השער. yatza hasha'ar. So I could just
go ahead, turn around and, let's say you gave me the five
pound bag of flour, it was worth five dollars, since in theory
I could take five dollars right now and go to the store
and buy it and hold onto it and give it back to
you later, so even if what I give it back to you
later it's a higher price, it's not a problem because it's like
I already have immediate access to that thing that I could give
you later. Even if you don't own it at the time? Even
if you don't own it at that time. That's the idea. If
it's יצא השער yatza hasha'ar and it's readily available, it's sort of
like you own it. Okay? So that's the other explanation, which is
a slightly more interesting one because it also gets to the whole
question of maybe that's why I can borrow a cup of flour,
because I can always just go to the store and buy it
at the store, okay? Even if right now the stores are closed,
I would have to wait for two, for a day or something,
the price is, you know, it's יצא השער, yatza hasha'ar, it's readily
available, so it's sort of like I already have that object, okay?
And if I already have the object, I'm allowed to borrow in
order to, you know, we're allowed to do a סאה בסאה se'ah
b'se'ah if I already own the object. Okay? So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's read that again.
אמר רב ששת אמר רב הונא אין לווין על שער שבשוק.
Amar Rav Sheshet amar Rav
Huna ein lovin al shaar shebashuk.
You can't borrow money based on, so here he's saying you're not
allowed to do it, based on the fixed market price. Either I
can't give you a hundred dollars and we'll call it a loan
and say if you don't pay me back the hundred dollars you'll
pay me back based on today's prices, because we're calling it a
loan, then when you pay me back the amount of fruit based
on today's prices that's going to be like ריבית. ribbis. Or what
it means is you can't borrow a cup of flour just because
it's available in the market and there's fixed prices, it's not like
you already have that cup of flour in which case you would
be able to borrow it. אמר ליה רב יוסף בר חמא לרב
ששת, ואמרי לה רב יוסי בר אבא לרב ששת: ומי אמר רב
הונא הכי? Amar lei Rav Yosef bar Chama le-Rav Sheshet, ve-amri lah
Rav Yosei bar Abba le-Rav Sheshet: U-mi amar Rav Huna hachi? Did
רב הונא Rav Huna really say that? והא בעו מיניה מרב הונא,
Ve-ha bau minei mei-Rav Huna, they asked רב הונא Rav Huna the
following question: הני בני בי רב דיזפי בתשרי ופרעי בטבת, Hanei benei
bei Rav d'yazpi be-Tishrei u-fari be-Teveis, these students, like ישיבה yeshiva students,
they borrow money in, they borrow in תשרי Tishrei and they pay
back in טבת. Teveis. So what are they borrowing? It either means
one of the two scenarios we just described. Either
a hundred dollars, but if I don't have the hundred dollars I'll
pay you back fruit based on today's prices. Okay? So that's exactly
the problem that we were describing, because you're calling it a loan
and if you're actually giving back not cash but fruit based on
today's prices, it's going to be worth more. Or the other thing
is that they could basically borrow like, you know, flour. They could
borrow bags of flour in order to make bread for themselves or
whatever, and they're going to pay back when they get their stipend
check, okay, and they'll pay back a three months from now, okay?
So they do that, and is that a סאה בסאה se'ah b'se'ah
problem? שרי או אסיר, Shari o assir, is that permissible or forbidden?
אמר להו, Amar lehu, הכי דהיני והכי דשילי. Hachi de-Hini v'hachi de-Shili.
Yeah, of course it's allowed. Look, there's grain available in היני Hini
and there's grain available in שילי, Shili, and you can go to
Stop and Shop, and you can go to Giveret, and you can
go to all these places, so of course you can go ahead
and do it. The grain is readily available. Okay, so it sounds
like he's saying it's מותר. mutar. So you said before you can't
do it, and now I'll tell you a statement that רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said you can do it. So what's the story? So
the גמרא, Gemara, אי בעו זימני ופרעי ליה מעיקרא. Ei ba'u zimni
upar-ei lei me-ikara. If
they want they could just buy it now and give it back
now, so it's like they already have the stuff. And because it's
like they already have it, it's acceptable. So it's either acceptable, which
is a big חידוש. chiddush. The first one is the bigger חידוש,
chiddush, that you can give money and call it a loan, and
once though the grain is readily available you can say I'm lending
you a hundred dollars, and if you don't pay me back the
hundred dollars you have to pay me back in grain based on
today's prices. And that's really acceptable, even though that when it's paid
back six months from now, you're getting back more money and you
even called it a loan. But because the guy could have just
gone ahead and bought the grain and held onto it. Okay, so
that's a big חידוש, chiddush, the first reading of רש"י. Rashi. The
second one is helpful to deal with our general case of borrowing
the cup of flour from your next-door neighbor. Sure you can borrow
it even though you don't have it, it's allowed to borrow a
cup of flour when you have a cup of flour, okay, but
even if you don't have it, if it's readily available and there's
fixed prices in the stores, you can just go get it in
the store, so of course you can borrow it from your neighbor.
Okay, so anyway, so it sounds like he's saying it's okay. So
what's the story? Before you said it wasn't okay. So the גמרא
Gemara said, מעיקרא סבר רב הונא אין לווין, Me-ikara savar Rav Huna
ein lovin, originally he held you couldn't. כיון דשמעיה להא דאמר רב
שמואל בר חייא אמר רבי אלעזר לווין, Keivan d'sham-ei l'ha d'amar Rav
Shmuel bar Chiya amar Rabbi Elazar lovin, but then he heard that
a statement in the name of שמואל Shmuel that you could do
it, אמר איהו נמי לווין, amar Ihu nami lovin, so he changed
his mind, fine. שמואל Shmuel says you can do it, I'll say
you can do it. It's interesting, like just based on the weight
of the authority, like not based on a different type of an
argument. Okay, so that was fascinating. If you read it that you
can actually frame it a loan, it's really fascinating, because that sounds
very fishy now. But if you read it as the case of
סאה בסאה, se'ah b'se'ah, it's very helpful why you can borrow a
cup of flour from your next-door neighbor. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
המוליך חבילה ממקום למקום. Hamolich chavila mimakom lemakom.
Now, you are going out and you're schlepping some wares from one
place to another. Okay, you are taking them from, you know, from
I don't know,
from אשכאש Ashkash to Manhattan. Manhattan's a much better market, you're going
to be able to get a much higher prices in Manhattan. ואמר
לו, V'amar lo, so now I bump into the guy who's taking
these wares, right? In אשכאש Ashkash they're selling for a dollar, in
Manhattan they're selling for two dollars, and I say to him the
following thing: תנה לי, Tna-li, give them to me, ואני אעלה לך
כדרך שמעלים לך באותו מקום. v'ani a-aleh lecha k'derech she-ma'alim lecha b'oso
makom. And I will pay you based on the price that you
would get. You have a hundred of these units,
give it to me
and I'll pay you two hundred dollars for them. That's the price
I'll get for them in Manhattan. So now why am I agreeing
to do that? I'm not going to get any profit. Why would
I agree to do that? I'm taking them from you here in
אשכאש, Ashkash, I still have to schlep them, what? Yeah, because I
once I have, because essentially it gives me accessible funds. That means
that once I'm in Manhattan I'll get the two hundred dollars in
Manhattan, I'll use that to make my own investments, I'll make some
money, I'll do some trading while I'm there, and then I'll come
back and I'll give you the two hundred dollars. So essentially, the
reason I'm paying you a higher price is because you're lending me
the money, because you're giving this to me, right? So do we
frame it like that? Do we frame it like essentially you lent
me money? Or do we frame it like no, I just purchased
the stuff at a higher price at, I agreed to pay you
a higher price to purchase your stuff. Okay? Is it a purchase,
right, which then it'll be allowed, okay, or is it a and
I'll pay you later, right, or is it a case of essentially
a type of a loan and I'm giving you money because of
you've lent me this and giving me access to funds?
Yeah, we saw similar things, yes we have, the whole case about
the what was it called? The case of
רב פפא, Rav Papa, the תרשא, tarsha, תרשא דרב פפא. Tarsha de-Rav
Papa. Okay, so anyway it says like this: ברשות מוכר מותר. Birshus
mocher mutar. If basically, it's interesting, if basically what we
say is that I sign, but I, I'm
agreeing, I'm the buyer in this scenario. Okay, so the seller is
going to sell to me, but he's agreeing that he accepts liability
if anything goes wrong with those wares between now and the time
I get them to Manhattan. happen and sell them. Okay, then it's
allowed. Why is it allowed? Because that means that what I'm doing
then is I'm שלעפינג shlepping his wares, I haven't bought them yet,
to Manhattan, and then when I sell them, I've sold his wares,
it's his $200. And at that moment, I have $200 of his
cash, and I'm borrowing $200, I'm going to pay back $200. So
then it's okay. Okay, but because, but, if basically I take liability,
that means that I take ownership of it right now. I took
ownership of something that was only
worth $100 and then I am essentially going and I'm going to
pay him $200. So I can't take ownership now. If I wanted
to pay cash, okay, if you wanted to pay cash, you could
pay whatever deal you want to enter into. You want to buy
stuff that costs $100, you want to pay $200 up front, געזונטהייט,
gezuntheyt, it's your money. But you're paying later, and because you're paying
later, it has a ריבית ribbis type of a problem to it.
So you can't buy now at a higher price to deliver the
money later. Okay, so if you took possession now and were to
pay later at a higher price than it's going for now, then
that's no good. That's a type of ריבית. ribbis. Okay, so ברשות
מוכר מותר, birshus moicher mutar, ברשות לוקח אסור. birshus loikeach assur. Now
תוספות Tosfos asks the obvious question. תוספות Tosfos says even if it's
ברשות מוכר מותר, birshus moicher mutar, I didn't essentially buy it till
I got it to Manhattan, but I still did you a huge
favor. What favor did I do to you? I שלעפד shlepped it
to Manhattan. Why am I doing you that favor of שלעפינג shlepping
it to Manhattan? Because you're going to lend me the money. You're
going to give me... like essentially I'm giving you this thing because
you're going to give me money, you're going to give me access
to funds. So תוספות Tosfos says we would have to say that
you're actually paying me for my שלעפינג. shlepping. Okay, but it's not
in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say that, but תוספות
Tosfos says that. All right. All right, so that's anyway one case.
All right, but the basic point though, important point is, I can't
purchase something now... this is really important, because this is the whole
point of יצא השער. yatza hashaar. I can't purchase something now and
pay you a higher price than the market price unless I am
paying you up front. If I'm paying you later, I have to
pay, then I have to pay you the market price. If I'm
agreeing to a higher price, it's sort of like the whole טרשא,
tarsha, right? You can't agree to a higher price for later payment.
Okay, so if you're not paying now, you have to do it
at today's prices. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: המוליך פירות ממקום למקום. Hamolich peiros mimakom lemakom.
Now, similarly, you're שלעפינג shlepping the fruit from one place to another.
מצא חברו ואמר לו תנם לי ואני אעלה לך פירות שיש לי
באותו מקום. Matza chaveiro veamar lo, tneim li vaani alecha peiros sheyesh
li beoso makom. Okay, now that's a little bit different.
Okay, basically, you're שלעפינג shlepping the fruit. And let me just hold
on, let me just double check רש"י Rashi to just say...
one minute.
Oh right. You now, you don't want to resell them, you want
to eat them. Okay, so basically, you're bringing your fruit from Oshkosh
to Manhattan where the prices are higher. Actually I was surprised to
find out... I always assumed, whatever, I always assumed everything is more
expensive in Manhattan because of rents or whatever, then I went... but
actually the price of fruit and other stuff often is more expensive
out of Manhattan, which has to do with supply and demand, I
guess, or whatever. Anyway, whatever, doesn't matter. You have this stuff in
Oshkosh here, okay, I'm hungry, I want to eat them right now,
all right? You want to bring them to Manhattan to make money
off of them. So what I'll say to you is the following.
I'll say look, give them to me right now so I can
eat them and feed my family, and then I actually do have
fruit up in Manhattan and I'll give you back this, you know,
whatever, this bushel of fruit up in Manhattan and you can sell
it there and make the same profit you would have made. Okay,
you won't do the שלעפינג. shlepping. You'll give it to me now,
I'll eat it now, we'll both go to Manhattan, I'll give it
to you there, I'll tell someone, tell them to give it to
you there, whatever, and then you'll be able to sell the fruit
there at a profit. Okay, so there's a bit of a problem.
Problem is that that's a סאה בסאה. sa besa. I'm taking something
now and I'm giving you one unit now, I'm giving you back
a unit later, and I'm actually... it's even worse than a סאה
בסאה, sa besa, because I'm actually giving you back a unit later
in a context where we know it's worth more money. I'm going
to give you back that unit in that other location where it
actually is worth more money. Okay, so what's the story? Okay, let's
take a look. אם יש לו פירות באותו מקום מותר. Im yesh
lo peiros beoso makom mutar.
If you have the fruit there, it's allowed, because remember, I said
that סאה בסאה sa besa was allowed when you owned it even
if it wasn't immediately accessible. Now again, this is a bigger חידוש
chiddush because this is not just I've got it, it's in my
apartment or whatever, right, this is actually the place that I have
it in, it is more expensive. Okay, so it's definitely a bigger
חידוש. chiddush. Okay. אם יש לו באותו מקום מותר ואם לאו אסור.
Im yesh lo beoso makom mutar veim lav assur. Okay, but if
not it's forbidden. Okay,
fine.
Now...
right... one minute. Okay, fine. So moving on. So that's a bigger...
a bit of a חידוש chiddush because clearly it's worth more in
that other place. Okay, והחמרין מעלין במקום היוקר כבמקום הזול ואינם חוששין.
veachamorin maalin bemakom hayoker kivemakom hazol veeinam chosheshin. Okay,
now this is an interesting thing. Here you are, you've got these
donkey drivers, but you know, whenever you say חמרין, chamorin, donkey drivers,
I always assumed it meant... They made their money by renting out
their donkeys, but apparently what they also, what they really are is
they're just merchants. They just own a lot of donkeys because the
way you bring your wares is whatever.
So, in one place prices are high, and the other place prices
are lower. Okay, they're going to go and they're going to, the
way this is the way רש"י Rashi explains the case. They're in
Manhattan where the stuff is at $2 a unit. Okay, they're going
to go bring it from Ashkash where they're going to buy it
at $1 a unit. They can go ahead to the people in
Manhattan and say, or the big, let's say, the bulk purchasers in
Manhattan and say, I will pre-sell you 100 units at the Ashkash
price, at a dollar a unit. Okay? I will, even though here
it's going at $2 a unit. And then you're allowed, now obviously
why would I do that? I'm not making a profit. Well, I'm
doing it because I need maybe some access to funds. Okay, so
I'm figuring out for what I'll sell him I won't make a
profit, I'll get $100 now, I'll pre-sell 100 units, okay, I won't
make any profit off of that, but at least it'll give me
access to those funds. Now that's a big problem, because you're lending
me $100 here, right? You know, the, you're giving me $100, we
said you could go buy שער שבשוק, shar shebashuk, but the שער
שבשוק shar shebashuk here is at $2 a unit. So what allows
you to agree to get something, $100 and delivery of something which
is going to, which right now in this place is worth $200,
right? So why is that allowed? So let's take a look. We'll
read it like רש"י Rashi and then I'll tell you how תוספות
Tosfos understands the case. החמרים hachamarim מעלין ma'alim במקום bemakom היוקר hayoker
ובמקום ubemakom הזול. hazol.
They can basically sell people in the, when they're, you know, pre-sell
or whatever at the, in the places of higher prices based on
the lower prices, ואינם veinam חוששין, chosheshin, and they don't have to
worry. Now why don't they have to worry? So מאי טעמא, mai
ta'ama, what's the reason? רב פפא אמר Rav Pappa amar ניחא להו
דמגלו להו תרעא, nicha lehu demaglu lehu tara,
because the fact that they have pre-sold this amount, okay? רש"י, Rashi,
let me just double check רש"י Rashi one, one more second, hold
on. Right. Basically, the, what now you sold me, I've pre-sold this
amount, so you've given me this $100. Now I go to Ashkash,
and I basically say, I got $100 ready to buy, you know,
your, your grain, right? Or you might, you know, whatever, it's a
lot of money. We could say $10,000. I pre-sold $10,000. I come
flush with cash to this, you know, to this, to this town
on the outskirts ready to buy up their stuff. So it's very
clear that I'm a businessman, I've got means, I've got whatever, people
are willing to sell me their stuff, it helps my reputation. So
I get a lot of benefits off of having that cash on
me, okay? And therefore, even though I gave you a deal, I
got something out of the deal. What did I get out of
the deal? That it helped my reputation, it let everybody know that
I was a merchant. There's only a little bit of a problem
here which is, yeah, that's why you pay interest in general, because
you get something out of the deal. You get the use of
the funds. So here too, you think, oh, well, you got something
out of having the money, you got that it helped your reputation.
Right, that's the prob-, isn't that the problem of interest? So, you
know, you get money, you get a benefit of the money, and
you pay interest. So רש"י Rashi says, it's interesting, remember the גמרא
Gemara said, the principle of interest is money you pay for delayed
compensation, for delayed being paid back, right? So רש"י Rashi says, this
isn't about because of delay. Okay? This isn't that because you're letting
me use the money for a period of time I'm paying you,
I'm, you know, for that. This is like, רש"י Rashi says even
if you would have to like pay up right away, of course
there has to be some time, it'd have to do its job
of letting people know you're flush with cash. But the point is,
even if you were to basically do pay back on the same
day, you would be willing, you know, to do this deal because
just having people knowing you have those funds is, you know, you
know, is helpful for your reputation. It's still very hard, because it
sounds a lot like exactly what interest is about. You benefit from
having the money, you're willing to pay for it. So because you
gave me the money, I'm going to give you a low price,
a price that's much lower in your town. Okay, but that רש"י
Rashi explains it that it's not because of delaying the repayment of
the money. Okay, we're going to finish this and then I'll tell
you what תוספות Tosfos says. תוספות Tosfos is bothered by that as
well. He says, give me a break. There's obviously a serious, you
know, a serious benefit here. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, רב פפא אמר Rav Pappa amar ניחא להו דמגלו
להו תרעא. nicha lehu demaglu lehu tara.
It's good that it's revealed to them that they are basically merchants,
that it publicizes that they're merchants. רב אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר
Rav Acha brei deRav Ika amar ניחא להו דמאזפי גבייהו, nicha lehu
demazpi gabaihu, which is a variation of it. No, no, no, what's
good is is that if you have so much cash, you know,
people are going to sell you at a lower price. Or actually
רש"י Rashi doesn't say just because you have so much cash, רש"י
Rashi actually says if people know that you bought, that you pre-sold
it at a, you know, at a dollar a unit, so they
feel a little רחמנות rachmanus on you, they want you to make
a profit. So they'll sell to you at 95 cents a unit.
I don't know if people have so much רחמנות, rachmanus, but anyway,
once it's known that that was the price you sold it at,
you'll actually be able to get it at a lower price. slightly
lower price here, that's why רש"י Rashi says it. מאי בינייהו? Mai
beinaiu?
What's the difference? איכא בינייהו תגרא חדתא, Ikka beinaiu tagra chadta, a
new merchant. Okay, where רש"י Rashi says if it's a new merchant,
maybe the publicity I mean which way does it go? Does the
you need the publicity more but they won't have רחמנות rachmanus on
you or is the flip? Anyway, it's a little you know whatever,
the different opinions which way that split goes. Anyway, that's רש"י's Rashi's
read. תוספות Tosafot does not like this, okay? And תוספות Tosafot says
for a multiple reasons. And תוספות Tosafot says no, the case of
the סוחרים sochrim is the following. Let me just quickly check תוספות.
Tosafot.
Yeah, תוספות Tosafot really does not like this. He thinks he's the
way רש"י Rashi describes it should be obvious ריבית ribbis problems. So
תוספות Tosafot says oh,
so תוספות Tosafot basically says that, okay, so he doesn't change it
radically, but he basically says I'm pre-selling there to Eli at a
dollar a unit, okay, but here's the here's the difference. The difference
is is that I'm going to go now to Ashkash and take
his hundred dollars and I'm going to buy it. From the that
moment on, it's his, okay. And therefore if something happens after if
something happens to those hundred units on the way back, some accident
happens or whatever, he loses out, okay. So actually, I am not
selling him in Ashkash, you know, he paid me a hundred, I'm
selling him stuff worth two hundred. I'm just taking his money and
I'm buying it for him in the place where there's a lower
price. And at that from that moment it's his, okay. But nevertheless,
I did benefit from that whole thing. I did him a favor
of buying it for him at a lower market, okay, but he
did me the favor of letting me use the money from the
time between the time I left Manhattan and got to Ashkash. I
had access to those funds. But anyway, for תוספות Tosafot it's a
much more limited benefit, okay. It's not like I really go ahead
and you give me a hundred dollars and I'm going to deliver
you something that's worth two hundred, you know, that's worth two hundred
here, right? I'm going to buy it with you for you with
that money in a place where it's lower. So I'm just doing
you the service of using your money to buy something at a
lower price, to buy something in a market that has that has
lower prices. Okay, so that's the variation that תוספות Tosafot has. All
right, let's keep on going.
The גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
בסורא אזלי ארבעה ארבעה. Besura azlei arba’ah arba’ah. Now in Sura, this
grain was going at like four units per dollar. בכפרי, Bekafri, in
this other place, אזלי שיתא שיתא, azlei shita shita, was going six
units per dollar.
יהב רב זוזי לחמרי. Yehav Rav zuzei lechamrei. So Rav, this is
basically the case of the חמרין. chamarin. He basically, he was in
he was in Sura where the prices were higher, right? If it's
four units per dollar, the prices are higher. He gave them
money, okay, and וקבילו עליה אונסא דאורחא, vekabbalu alei onsa de'orcha, he
agreed to be responsible if anything went wrong, you know, on the
journey. ושקל מינייהו חמשה, Veshakal mineihu chamsha, and he basically took delivery
of at the price so he paid for it here, but he
brought he rather than getting four units per dollar, he took he
took five units per dollar, because they were going to go over
to this place Kafri, they were going to buy it at six
or whatever, and he took delivery at so he brought it here
at four and he took delivery at five. So he he got
you know, he he got more for his money than he normally
would have gotten. So now the גמרא Gemara says ולישקול שיתא? velishkol
shita? I don't understand. You just said you can do this deal
with these donkey drivers, give them the money here, they buy it
at the lower thing, they deliver it to you whatever, and you
could do it based on the prices at that lower price, right?
So why here did he if he was giving the money, why
here didn't he just agree to get it at the six per
dollar, rather than four per dollar? That's the whole thing we said
you're allowed to do if these donkey drivers. So the גמרא Gemara
says אדם חשוב שאני. Adam chashuv shani. No, he was a person
of stature and therefore he wanted to set an example of trying
to be more distant with ריבית. ribbis. You're still not going to
totally give up a profit whatever, you know, but but he he
wanted to sort of set an example. Okay.
For תוספות, Tosafot, the idea that he was מקבל mekabel the אונס,
ones, you know, is relevant because תוספות Tosafot says that's part of
the whole question of like who's liable is sort of in which
direction. Yeah.
Wasn't labor an element in these considerations? In other words, you know,
this ריבית ribbis question of you're gaining
something.
Right, so that's why תוספות Tosafot as I mentioned earlier, and תוספות
Tosafot here as well also throws that in. I mean it's not
in the גמרא, Gemara, but תוספות Tosafot throws in, oh we're also
assuming you're paying the guy for the schlepping labor. But that's not
in the גמרא, Gemara, you know. So that's you're right, it's an
important question to ask, okay. All right. בעי מיניה רב אסי מרבי
יוחנן. Ba'ei minei Rav Assi me'Rabbi Yochanan. Let's try to do one
more case. Rav Assi asked Rabbi Yochanan. Okay, מה לעשות בגרוטאות כאן?
Ma la'asot bi-grutaos kan? How about doing this with like scrap metal?
Now the assumption being that maybe the reason this works is because,
you know, it's like it's a, it's always going to be the
same market. You always have the farmers or whatever. So when I'm
selling it to you, like רש"י Rashi says, if it's based on
the benefit I get of reputation, I get a good reputation amongst
the farmers. But here the assumption is some other things, it's very
hit or miss. Do people have, like, you know, if it's a
secondhand market, do people have the stuff to sell or not? So
this is the way רש"י Rashi frames it. The benefit I get
from, by arranging,
by you giving, you know, by the reason I'm giving you the
lower price is because I get this benefit, it helps my reputation.
The question is, maybe that's not so important in a market that's
a much more hit or miss market. You have different people selling
on different days. You know, people don't always have the same wares
to sell. That's sort of the way רש"י Rashi understands the question.
Okay?
Yeah, because it's not like a fixed market of sellers that I'm
developing a relationship with. That's the way רש"י Rashi explains it. All
right. So כאן, kan, אמר ליה, amar lei, בעי מיניה רבי ישמעאל
ברבי יוסי לעשות כן ba'ei minei Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yose la'asot kein
בכלי פשתן be-klei pishtan ולא הניחו velo hinicho רבי. Rebbi.
No, you know what? רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yose
wanted to do this to sort of sell, you know,
sell here at where the prices were higher, you know, based on,
you know, the lower prices in the other place,
and in these like, you know, in garments, כלי פשתן, klei pishtan,
which I guess is also, you know, it's not like a grain
market, right? These are all handmade and whatever, so it's not the
same type of a large market and a stable market, and רבי
Rebbi did not allow him. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, some say, בעי
מיניה רבי לעשות כן בגרוטאות. ba'ei minei Rebbi la'asot kein bi-grutaos. איכא
דאמרי, Ika de-amri, בעי
מיניה רבי לעשות כן בגרוטאות כאן. ba'ei minei Rebbi la'asot kein bi-grutaos
kan. No, no, he wanted actually do it exactly with this case
of scrap metal, ולא הניחו רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. velo hinicho Rabbi
Yishmael be-Rabbi Yose. רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yose did
not allow him. So one of them was stopping the other one.
Okay. Anyway, the point here being what this is doing is this
is exploring this idea of יצא השער, yatza ha-sha'ar, but it's saying
if the שער sha'ar is not the שער sha'ar here, you want
to make an arrangement based on a שער sha'ar in a different
place where you're going to buy it, but there and there the
שער sha'ar is lower, but here the שער sha'ar is higher, that
should be a ריבית ribbis issue, but maybe it's not, but because
again, you're benefiting from it or so on, or according to תוספות,
Tosafos, you're really buying it for me there. But on the other
hand, maybe it all still even that still requires a certain amount
of a stable and a, sort of a big market. Okay. Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Let's do one more.
Okay.
פרדיסא. Pardisa. What about a garden or what רש"י Rashi says in
another place this means a, a vineyard? Okay. Now the question here
is, what are you buying with the vineyard? So basically, let me
just
get רש"י. Rashi. Okay.
So basically what you're doing is you're going to pre-buy, you're going
to go to a, the owner of a vineyard. You're going to
pre-buy wine. The fruit is very unripe. It's not יצא השער. yatza
ha-sha'ar. People don't even sell the fruit yet because it's not yet
ripe and there's not yet a fixed price. Okay. So I mean,
well they do sell it, but there's not a fixed price. It's
not yet, you know, the time to be sold. Okay. And you're
going to pre-buy based on low prices of today with this unripe
fruit, but you basically want delivery in terms of the wine. Okay.
So I go to you, you've got this vineyard, you've got this
acre here in your vineyard and I say, I'm going to pay
you now for what this acre goes for, which is pretty low
because the stuff is unripe at this stage. Okay. But I'm going
to give you today's prices and you're going to deliver to me
the wine. All right. Now that's a little bit of a problem
because that's sort of like the issue before, like the old and
the new or whatever, and what you're going to deliver is not
the same of what you're going to, what you're buying, right? What's
available now is this, is these grapes, and what you're delivering is
wine, which is worth a lot more. So let's take a look.
So it says like this. פרדיסא. Pardisa. רב אסר. Rav assar. רב
Rav said it's forbidden, אסר, assar, forbidden. ושמואל שרי. u-Shmuel shari. רב
אסר. Rav assar. רב Rav says it's forbidden. כיון דלכי מטי שוי
טפי. keivan delichi mati shavi tfei. It's going to be worth more
later. מתחזי כי אגר נטר ליה. mitchazi ki agar natar lei. It's
like you're getting money for holding on to it. ושמואל שרי. u-Shmuel
shari. שמואל Shmuel says it's permissible. כיון דהוה ביעתותא keivan de-hava bi'asuta
no, because there
is a certain amount of risk, then it's not אגר נטר, agar
natar, which basically means, all of the stuff could spoil and then
you're not just promising him delivery this gets back to David I
think a similar question asked before. You're not just promising delivery of
X bottles of wine. You're promising him delivery of wine from the
vineyard. So it's possible that all that wine will spoil and all
the whole vineyard will spoil, there'll be a, you know, there'll be
some terrible drought or something of that nature and there'll be no
wine at the vineyard. So you are accepting a certain element of
risk. Okay. So it's not like you're certain you're paying now and
you're definitely going to be getting something you're not just promised delivery
of wine, you're getting wine from the vineyard. So
therefore
Right, right, exactly, but a futures market you know you would have
to find somebody to sell it to if you sold a futures
no futures was before because before you're not selling a particular concrete
object right and here that if I'm selling you a future I
don't have it or whatever I just have to deliver the thing
to you I have to figure out where I'm going to get
it from. Here you're as the reason that makes it permissible here
is because you're selling something concrete, you're selling wine from the vineyard.
Okay now it might not be wine of a particular acre, if
some of the vineyard got destroyed and others didn't, I would still
be entitled to say I got an acre's worth of wine I'm
going to get that acre's worth not this acre's worth, but nevertheless
it's possible that the whole thing will be destroyed and therefore it
says it's okay because you are the purchase is more real and
there's an element of risk. Let's just finish this up.
אמר רב שימי בר אשי Amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi ומודי רב
u-modei Rav בטורי be-tori דנפיש פסידא הוא. de-nafish psida hu. And Rav
would agree who says that it's that it's forbidden that if it's
a case of טורי tori which is a debate what it means
but רשי Rashi says it means an area that you plow with
oxen and therefore there's more risk involved in that of things getting
damaged so then he would also agree that that would be fine
because there is again this higher element of risk makes it permissible
even though you're selling stuff at a higher price than it's going
for now. אמר להו שמואל להנהו דשבשי שבשא. Amar le-hu Shmuel le-hanhu
de-shabshei shabsha. Shmuel said to the people that are שבשי שבשא shabshei
shabsha which רשי Rashi says basically
means well I'm going to skip רשי Rashi because תוספות Tosafot explains
it very nicely in terms of what we're just reading that basically
it means exactly these people
that they're
selling that they're people that are buying you know from
the pre-buying the wine from the people that are basically you know
that own
the vines okay they're pre-buying the wine so he says to them
הפוכו בארעא כי היכי דתקנו לכו גופא דארעא. Hafukhu be-ara ki heikhi
de-tiknu lakhu gufa de-ara. So go ahead and like you know till
the ground a little bit so you're actually taking a little possession
of the land itself.
ואי לא הוי לכו כהלוואה ואסיר. Ve-i lo havei lakhu ke-halva'ah ve-asir.
If not it'll be like a loan and it's forbidden. So this
was similar to the previous case. Okay you're buying the stuff while
it's still on the grapes but you're on the vine and but
you're trying to get delivery of the wine itself right and and
that's obviously a bit you know more of a problem because it's
clearly going to be worth more as wine and we just conceptualized
it before that the reason it's okay is because you're assuming an
element of risk so that makes it more like a purchase. So
here the way it's being dealt with is do a little קנין
kinyan on the ground so it's sort of like you're taking a
tiny percentage of the vineyard itself you're buying a percentage of the
vineyard itself and it's not as much of a loan and therefore
it'll be okay. All right so a lot of very wide range
of different practical cases which makes it you know more than the
גמרא Gemara generally a lot of
abstractions but we're starting to see how this stuff gets applied. Okay.